A Guide to the Works Projects Administration of Virginia Records, 1939-1943
Library of Virginia
- Series I. Historical Records Survey.
  - Subseries 5. Court Abstracts and Transcripts.
    - Richmond City, 1911-1916. (Box 535)
      Hustings Court Order Books 53-60, 1911-1916.
    - Roanoke City, 1884-1909. (Box 536)
      Order Books 1-26, 1884-1909.
    - Roanoke City, 1909-1917. (Box 537)
      Order Books 27-35, 1909-1917.
    - Roanoke City, 1917-1921. (Box 538)
      Order Books 36-41, 1917-1921.
    - Roanoke City, 1921-1926. (Box 539)
      Order Books 42-50, 1921-1926.
    - Roanoke City, 1926-1931. (Box 540)
      Order Book 51-60, 1926-1931.
    - Roanoke City, 1931-1939. (Box 541)
      Order Book 61-75, 1931-1939.
    - Roanoke City, 1910-1939. (Box 542)
      Law and Chancery Court Common Law Order Books 1-13, 1910-1939.
    - Roanoke City, 1884-1926. (Box 543)
      Chancery Order Books 1-10, 1884-1904 and Chancery Order Books 1-7, 1910-1926.
    - Roanoke City, 1926-1939. (Box 549)
      Chancery Order Books 8-18, 1926-1939.
  - Subseries 6. Miscellaneous Programs.
    Consists of information on miscellaneous programs run by the W.P.A, including the School Lunch program, Nutrition Camps of Virginia, and the Feeding Project of Virginia.
    - Miscellaneous Programs. (Box 545-547)
  - Subseries 7. Virginia Historical Inventory.
    This subseries has been digitized and is available online. The manuscript copies are available in Special Collections at the Library of Virginia.
- II. Virginia Writers Project.
  This series consists of eleven subseries: 1. Historical Files; 2. Handbook of Procedures; 3. Radio Plays; 4. Life Histories; 5. Biographical Files; 6. Mimeographed Pamphlets; 7. Manuscripts of Published Works; 8. Statewide History; 9. Unfinished Books; 10. Printed Books; and 11. Feature Articles.
  - Subseries 1. Historical Files.
    Consists of handwritten research sheets on the origins of counties and cities and famous people, buildings, events, and battles that occurred in the corresponding areas.
    - County of Albemarle. (Box 122-124)
    - County of Dinwiddie. (Box 125-129)
    - County of Princess Ann and Municipality of Norfolk. (Box 130-138)
    - County of Sussex. (Box 139-141)
    - County of Warren. (Box 142-146)
    - Counties of Accomack-Augusta. (Box 147)
    - Counties of Bath-Campbell. (Box 148)
    - Counties of Campbell-Charlotte. (Box 149)
    - Counties of Chesterfield-Fairfax. (Box 150)
    - Counties of Fauquier-Franklin. (Box 151)
    - County of Franklin. (Box 152)
    - Counties of Franklin-Goochland. (Box 153)
    - Counties of Grayson-Henrico. (Box 154)
    - Counties of Henrico-Lancaster. (Box 155)
    - Counties of Lee-Northampton. (Box 156)
    - Counties of Northumberland-Prince William. (Box 157)
    - Counties of Pulaski-Richmond. (Box 158)
    - Counties of Rockbridge-Southampton. (Box 159)
    - Counties of Spotsylvania-Wise. (Box 160)
    - Counties of Wythe-York and Miscellaneous. (Box 161)
    - Municipalities of Alexandria-Fredericksburg. (Box 162)
    - Municipality of Fredericksburg. (Box 163-164)
    - Municipalities of Hampton-Newport News. (Box 165)
    - Municipalities of Norfolk-Winchester. (Box 166)
    - Municipality of Winchester. (Box 167)
  - Subseries 2. Handbook of Procedures.
    Consists of Handbook of Procedures for State and District Works Projects Administration.
    - Handbook of Procedures for State and District Works Projects Administration. (Box 168)
  - Subseries 3. Radio Plays.
    Consists of typewritten radio plays by Virginia Writers' Project employees.
    - Radio Plays. (Box 169-176)
    - Radio Plays, Including "Virginia Traveler Contest Letters". (Box 177)
    - Radio Plays. (Box 553-554)
  - Subseries 4. Life Histories.
    Consists of approximately 1,350 life histories, social-ethnic studies, and youth studies plus more than 50 interviews with former slaves which were created by the staff of the Virginia Writers' Project. The life histories are available on microfilm on Misc. Reels 1846-1853. The life histories have also been digitized and are available online. Click here to learn about the WPA Life Histories Collection or click here to search and view the collection online.
    - Life Histories 00001-00067. (Box 178)
    - Life Histories 00068-00126. (Box 179a)
    - Life Histories 00127-00173. (Box 179b)
    - Life Histories 00174-00236. (Box 180)
    - Life Histories 00237-00292. (Box 181a)
    - Life Histories 00293-00355. (Box 181b)
    - Life Histories 00356-00445. (Box 182)
    - Life Histories 00446-00509. (Box 183)
    - Life Histories 00510-00563. (Box 184a)
    - Life Histories 00564-00593. (Box 184b)
    - Life Histories 00594-00649. (Box 185)
    - Life Histories 00650-00698. (Box 186a)
    - Life Histories 00699-00773. (Box 186b)
    - Life Histories 00774-00836. (Box 187a)
    - Life Histories 00837-00857. (Box 187b)
    - Life Histories 00893-00935. (Box 188a)
    - Life Histories 00858-00892. (Box 188b)
    - Life Histories 00936-00984. (Box 189a)
    - Life Histories 00985-01016. (Box 189b)
    - Life Histories 01017-01111. (Box 190a)
    - Life Histories 01112-01163. (Box 190b)
    - Life Histories 01164-01222. (Box 191/1)
    - Life Histories 01223-01274. (Box 191/2)
    - Life Histories 01275-01367. (Box 191a/1)
      Ex-Slave Interviews.
    - Life Histories 01368-01427. (Box 191a/2)
    - Life Histories. (Box 191b)
      Duplicates of Boxes 178-180.
    - Life Histories. (Box 191c)
      Duplicates of Boxes 181-184.
    - Life Histories. (Box 191d)
      Duplicates of Boxes 183-187.
    - Life Histories. (Box 191e)
    - Life Histories. (Box 191f)
      Duplicates of Boxes 190-191a. Handwritten duplicates.
  - Subseries 5. Biographical Files.
    Consists of biographies, including finished papers and handwritten and typewritten notes on notable Virginia citizens, such as doctors, governors, and jurists.
    Arranged alphabetically by last name.
    - Abernathy-Bayley. (Box 192)
    - Bellini-Bray. (Box 193)
    - Richard Bland and miscellaneous folders. (Box 194)
    - Miscellaneous Subjects. (Box 195)
    - Breckinridge-Campbell, Malcolm. (Box 196)
    - Campbell, William-Cocke Family. (Box 197)
    - Coke-Side File "D through F". (Box 198)
    - Dabney-Dysart. (Box 199)
    - Each-Side File "I through J". (Box 200)
    - Fain-Gmelin. (Box 201)
    - G-H. (Box 202)
    - Heath-Ivey. (Box 203)
    - Jackson Family-Julian. (Box 204)
    - Kegley-Side File "M". (Box 205)
    - Lackaye-Lyons. (Box 206)
    - MacBane-Mason. (Box 207)
    - Massey-Myers. (Box 208)
    - Nash-Pattilloo; Side File "N,P,R,S"; Information on Redford and Sussex County School Statistics. (Box 209)
    - Patton-Purefoy. (Box 210)
    - Redford-Sevier. (Box 211)
    - Shanks-Stover. (Box 212)
    - Strachan-Van Lew. (Box 213)
    - Van Meter-Wetmore. (Box 214)
    - Warton-"Z". (Box 215)
    - Side File "T"-"Y". (Box 216)
    - Book of Facts, "A-1" through "B-6"; Russell Papers. (Box 217)
    - Book of Facts, "B-7" through "F-3". (Box 218)
    - Book of Facts, "G-1" through "K". (Box 219)
    - Book of Facts, "L-1" through "N-3". (Box 220)
    - Book of Facts, "O" through "R-8". (Box 221)
    - Book of Facts, "R-9" through "T-4". (Box 222)
    - Book of Facts, "T-5" through "Y-1"; Virginia State Tax Bulletins,1939-1941. (Box 223)
    - Book of Facts, Counties of Albemarle and Dinwiddie; Carter's Index, "A-R". (Box 224)
    - Book of Facts, Carter's Index, "S-Z". (Box 225)
    - Religious Leaders, A-F. (Box 226)
    - Religious Leaders, "R-1" through end; Nathaniel Francis Cabell, Thomas Massie, and miscellaneous; Statesmen, "A" through end. (Box 227)
    - Jurists, "B" through end; 17th through 19th Century Doctors. (Box 228)
    - Half Sheet File, "A" through "M-2". (Box 235)
    - Half Sheet File, "M-3" through "Y". (Box 236)
    - Cross Index. (Box 237-240)
  - Subseries 6. Mimeographed Pamphlets.
    Consists of copies of papers and stories written by the Virginia Writers' Project on various subjects.
    - Extra Mimeographed Pamphlets. (Box 229-232)
    - Mimeographed Pamphlets. (Box 552)
  - Subseries 7. Manuscripts of Published Works.
    Consists of typed versions of papers and pamphlets written as part of the Virginia Writers' Project.
    - Manuscripts of Published Books. (Box 233-234)
  - Subseries 8. Statewide History.
    Papers and articles written on a variety of Virginia subjects as part of the Virginia Writers' Project.
    - Agriculture-National Defense. (Box 241)
    - National Resources-National Wonders. (Box 242)
    - Northern Neck-Newspapers. (Box 243)
    - Newspapers-Points of Interest. (Box 244)
    - Publications-Religious Denominations. (Box 245)
    - Roads-Social Life. (Box 246)
    - Social Life. (Box 247)
    - State Emblems-Transportation. (Box 248)
    - History, Explorers through Colonial, 1607-1736. (Box 249)
    - History, Revolutionary Period, 1777-1781 through Civil War, Battles and Campaigns. (Box 250)
    - History, Suffrage through Virginia. (Box 251)
    - Governors, Bennett-Berkeley. (Box 252)
    - Governors, Culpeper-Raleigh. (Box 253)
    - Governors, Randolph-Yeardley. (Box 254)
  - Subseries 9. Unfinished Books.
    - Unfinished Books. (Box 255-256)
    - Important Manuscripts. (Box 257-259)
  - Subseries 10. Printed Books.
    - Printed Books. (Box 551-552)
  - Subseries 11. Feature Articles.
    - Feature Articles. (Box 553)
- Series III. Clipping Files.
  Consists of newspaper clippings from various Virginia daily and weekly newspapers.
  Arranged alphabetically by city or county name, with miscellaneous arranged to the front.
  - Clippings, 9 October 1933-June 1936. (Box 345)
  - Various state newspapers, 15 June-August 1936. (Box 346)
  - Abingdon Journal-Virginian through [Amelia C. H.] Gazette. (Box 347)
  - Amherst New Era-Progress through [Berryville] Clarke Courier. (Box 348)
  - [Big Stone Gap] Post through [Bristol] Herald-Courier. (Box 349)
  - [Bristol] Herald-Courier through Buchanan News. (Box 350)
  - [Cape Charles] Northampton Times through [Clarksville] Mecklenburg Times. (Box 351)
  - [Clifton Forge] Daily Review through [Covington] Virginian. (Box 352)
  - [Covington] Virginian through Danville Herald. (Box 353)
  - Danville Register through [Dillwyn] Buckingham Times. (Box 354)
  - [Drake's Branch] Charlotte Gazette through [Franklin] Tidewater News. (Box 355)
  - [Fredericksburg] Free Lance-Star through [Galax] Post-Herald. (Box 356)
  - [Gate City] Herald through [Harrisonburg] Daily News-Record. (Box 357)
  - [Harrisonburg] Daily News-Record through [Hopewell] News. (Box 358)
  - [Kenbridge] Free State News through [Lovingston] Nelson County News. (Box 359)
  - [Luray] Page News and Courier through [Lynchburg] Daily Advance. (Box 360)
  - [Lynchburg] Daily Advance through [Lynchburg] News. (Box 361)
  - [Lynchburg] News. (Box 362)
  - [Lynchburg] News through [Martinsville] Daily Bulletin. (Box 363)
  - [Martinsville] Daily Bulletin through [Newport News] Daily News. (Box 364)
  - [Newport News] Daily Press. (Box 365)
  - [Newport News] Daily Press through [Newport News] Times-Herald. (Box 366)
  - [Newport News] Times-Herald through [Norfolk] Ledger-Dispatch. (Box 367)
  - [Norfolk] Ledger-Dispatch. (Box 368)
  - [Norfolk] News-Index through [Norfolk] Virginian-Pilot. (Box 369)
  - [Norfolk] Virginian-Pilot through Orange Review. (Box 370)
  - [Palmyra] Midlands-Virginian through [Petersburg] Progress-Index. (Box 371)
  - [Petersburg] Progress-Index through [Petersburg] Southside Virginia News. (Box 372)
  - Portsmouth Star. (Box 373)
  - Portsmouth Star through [Radford] Evening Star. (Box 374)
  - Radford News-Journal through Richmond News-Leader. (Box 375)
  - Richmond News-Leader. (Box 376-378)
  - Richmond News-Leader through Richmond Times-Dispatch. (Box 379)
  - Richmond Times-Dispatch. (Box 380-383)
  - Roanoke Leader through Roanoke Times. (Box 384)
  - Roanoke Times. (Box 385-386)
  - [Roanoke] World-News. (Box 387)
  - [Roanoke] World-News through [Rustburg] Campbell County Times. (Box 388)
  - [Salem] Times-Register through [Staunton] Evening Leader. (Box 389)
  - [Staunton] News-Leader. (Box 390)
  - [Staunton] News-Leader through [Suffolk] News-Herald. (Box 391)
  - [Suffolk] News-Herald through Virginia Beach News. (Box 392)
  - [Wakefield] Tri-County News through Waynesboro News-Virginian. (Box 393)
  - Waynesboro News-Virginian through Winchester Evening Star. (Box 394)
  - [Woodstock] Shenandoah Herald through [Wytheville] Wythe County News. (Box 395)
    Includes obituary notices for William A. Smith, State W.P.A. Head, 1940; miscellaneous newspapers and magazines, 1938-1942, and booklet on reporting physical progress and accomplishments on Certified Defense Projects.
  - Duplicate Clippings. (Box 396)
- Series IV. Photographs.
  This series consists of photographs taken of various W.P.A related projects including sewage construction in Prince George and Westmoreland Counties, demolition of Virginia Hall at Virginia State College, and installation of storm drains in Norfolk County.
  - Photographs, 1937. (Box 554)
- Series V. Miscellaneous Files.
  - Office Files from Van Schreevan, 1942. (Box 548)
    Consists of office files of employees of the Works Projects Administration. Also includes a minute book, 1933-1936, of the Virginia Emergency Relief Administration.